"The Benefits of Quinine (Tonic Water)
to Suppress Hunger and Boost GLP-1"
Most of the poisons
used by humans
come from bitter plants.
For example,
strychnine and hemlock.
At the same time,
some of the most
popular beverages
in the world are bitter,
as are some
of the healthiest foods.
Bitter taste receptors
aren’t only on our tongue,
but throughout much
of our digestive tract,
on the very same cells
lining our gut that secrete
the appetite-suppressing
hormone, GLP-1.
And indeed,
a number of bitter compounds
have been shown
to potently stimulate
the release of hormones
like GLP-1
in Petri dishes and lab animals.
What about people?
And beer!
Beer is one of the most popular
bitter beverages,
thanks to hops.
Given that bitter herbs
have evidently been used
in times of scarcity
to reduce hunger,
researchers tested low and high
doses of hops extracts
on people undergoing
a 24-hour fast,
and found both doses seemed
to lower feelings of hunger
better than placebo.
Might that be a GLP-1 effect?
Let’s find out.
Taking a hops extract
before a meal,
in either immediate
or delayed-release capsules,
led to significantly more
GLP-1 release
than did a placebo.
And, more importantly,
when the study participants
were given
all-you-can-eat ham sandwiches
a few hours later,
they ate significantly less.
They didn’t feel significantly
less hungry or more full,
but, overall, still ate
about 200 calories less.
So, a bitter hop extract
significantly decreased
calorie intake,
while increasing
appetite-suppressing hormones,
like GLP-1.
These changes occurred
without the participants
feeling any different,
appetite-wise,
or liking the sandwiches
any less.
Now, the extract
did make them feel
nauseated, bloat-y, and barf-y,
but maybe
that’s just more evidence
it might be working
through GLP-1,
since those are
common side effects
of the GLP-1-mimicking drugs,
like Ozempic.
Well, wait,
no wonder they ate less,
but evidently, the degree
of gastrointestinal discomfort
did not correlate
with how much less they ate.
The main reason
I’d caution against hops
is because of a compound in hops
called 8-PN
that I’ve talked about before
in a two-part video series.
What about quinine,
perhaps the best-studied
bitter substance
in human history?
Extracted from the bark
of the cinchona tree,
quinine was not only
the first effective treatment
for malaria 400 years ago,
but, remarkably,
remains a common and effective
treatment to this day.
And give someone
275 milligrams of it,
and GLP-1 secretion
is stimulated.
Enough to actually reduce
appetite and body weight?
"Dietary quinine reduces
body weight and food intake,"
in rats.
What about in people?
"Intragastric
quinine administration
decreases hedonic eating,"
meaning eating for pleasure,
even if you aren’t
really hungry.
In this case,
a chocolate milkshake.
And if you’re thinking,
"Well, of course
they’d drink less milkshake
if they just had something
super bitter," but, no.
The quinine was administered
directly into their stomach
through a tube,
so it bypassed the bitter
receptors in their mouth.
There are still
those bitter receptors
in our gut, though,
that we aren’t even
consciously aware of.
The researchers
even did brain scans,
and concluded that
being unknowingly slipped
about 200 milligrams of quinine
not only affected
how much the study participants
felt like they wanted to eat,
but how much
they actually did eat,
by interfering
with reward brain circuits.
And you don’t have to go
lick some tree bark to get it.
It’s available
in every grocery store
in the form of tonic water.
A liter of tonic water has about
60 to 70 milligrams of quinine,
and bitter lemon,
another popular cocktail mixer,
has about half that.
But getting
200 milligrams of quinine
still would be like drinking
three quarts of tonic water.
Can we get away with less?
Yes.
In this study, people were given
just 18 milligrams of quinine,
or placebo,
and then, an hour later,
everyone was given
all-you-can-eat
ham and cheese sandwiches.
And caloric intake
was significantly lower
after the quinine than placebo
by about 14 percent.
So, drinking a third of a liter
of tonic water before a meal
could reduce your caloric intake
by 82 calories.
But a third of a liter
of tonic water
has more than
a hundred calories!
So, that wouldn’t
do you much good.
Tonic water is basically
quinine-spiked
carbonated sugar water.
Now, there are
sugar-free varieties,
or, you could go
straight to the source.
What if you got about
the same amount of quinine
in the form of powdered bark?
The effects of giving about
a third of a teaspoon a day
of powdered cinchona bark
on satiety, weight loss,
and body composition
in a population
of overweight adults.
Significantly more weight loss,
significantly more waist lost,
and even slimmer hips
in the bark group,
compared to placebo,
and the weight loss
was in fat mass,
with greater
lean mass preservation,
compared to placebo.
So, in humans,
quinine may boost GLP-1,
decrease hedonic hunger,
lower appetite,
decrease calorie intake,
and decrease body fat.
What are the downsides?
That’s what I’ll cover next.